When I was considering a career in the art world,
خلال تفكيري بالعمل في مجال الفن
I took a course in London,
التحقت بدورة في لندن
and one of my supervisors was this irascible Italian
حيث كان هناك مشرف غضوب ايطالي الجنسية
called Pietro, who drank too much,
كان اسمه بيترو، كان يشرب كثيراً
smoked too much and swore much too much.
ويدخن كثيراً وكان سليط اللسان كثيراً كثيراً
But he was a passionate teacher,
لكنه كان معلماً شغوفا ملئياً بالطاقة
and I remember one of our earlier classes with him,
في أحد الدروس الأولى له
he was projecting images on the wall,
كان يطلب منا التفكير في بعض الصور
asking us to think about them,
التي كان يعرضها على الحائط
and he put up an image of a painting.
ثم قام بعرض صورة للوحة
It was a landscape with figures, semi-dressed,
كانت تحتوي على أشخاص شبه عارين
drinking wine. There was a nude woman
يشربون الخمر. من ضمنهم إمرأة عارية
in the lower foreground, and on the hillside in the back,
تقف في المقدمة، وعلى الهضبة الموجود في خلفية الصورة
there was a figure of the mythological god Bacchus,
كان الإله الاسطوري "باخوس"
and he said, "What is this?"
سألنا المعلم "ماهذا ؟"
And I -- no one else did, so I put up my hand, and I said,
فرفعت يدي لوحدي من بين جميع الطلاب
"It's a Bacchanal by Titian."
وأجبت "إنها العربيد لتيتان"
He said, "It's a what?"
فاستغرب من جوابي
I thought maybe I'd pronounced it wrong.
فاعتقدت أني قمت بلفظها بشكل خاطئ
"It's a Bacchanal by Titian."
فقلت مرة أخرى إنها "العربيد لتيتان"
He said, "It's a what?"
فاستغرب مرة أخرى
I said, "It's a Bacchanal by Titian." (Laughter)
فقلت إنها "العربيد لتيتان" (ضحك)
He said, "You boneless bookworm!
فاستهزء باجابتي
It's a fucking orgy!"
وقال: "إنها عربدة وجنس جماعي"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
As I said, he swore too much.
لقد كان سليط اللسان كما قلت لكم
There was an important lesson for me in that.
لقد تعلمت درساً مهماً من ذلك
Pietro was suspicious of formal art training,
لم يكن بيترو مقتنعاً بتعليم الفن
art history training, because he feared
أو التاريخ، لأنه كان يتخوف
that it filled people up with jargon, and then they just
من أن التعليم الرسمي يملئ رؤوس الطلاب بالتعابير الاصطلاحية مما يؤدي
classified things rather than looking at them,
إلى قيامهم بتصنيف الأشياء عوضاً عن التمعن بها
and he wanted to remind us that all art was once contemporary,
وأراد تذكيرنا أن كل أنواع الفنون كانت معاصرة في وقتها
and he wanted us to use our eyes,
وأرادنا أن ننظر بتجرد
and he was especially evangelical about this message,
وقد كان مؤمناً بأهمية إيصال هذه الرسالة
because he was losing his sight.
لأنه كان على وشك أن يفقد بصره
He wanted us to look and ask basic questions of objects.
أرادنا أن ننظر بتجرد ونتسائل بتجرد
What is it? How is it made? Why was it made?
عن مانرى. وعن الكيفية التي تم صنع مانراه بها وعن سبب صنعه
How is it used?
وكيفية استخدامه؟
And these were important lessons to me when
وقد استفدت جيداً من تلك الدروس المهمة، حيث
I subsequently became a professional art historian.
أصبحت بعدها مؤرخاً للفن
My kind of eureka moment came a few years later,
لحظة الحقيقة بالنسبة لي كانت بعد عدة سنوات
when I was studying the art of the courts of Northern Europe,
حيث كنت أدرس "فن المحاكم في أوربا الشمالية"
and of course it was very much discussed in terms of
وكان النقاش معتمداً على
the paintings and the sculptures
الرسومات والمجسمات
and the architecture of the day.
والعمارة، في ذلك الوقت.
But as I began to read historical documents
وأثناء اطلاعي على بعض الوثائق التاريخية
and contemporary descriptions,
والشروحات المعاصرة
I found there was a kind of a missing component,
لاحظت أن هناك حلقة مفقودة
for everywhere I came across descriptions of tapestries.
في كل مرة اطلعت فيها على شروحات عن المنسوجات
Tapestries were ubiquitous between the Middle Ages
كانت المنسوجات منتشرة بكثرة في العصور الوسطى
and, really, well into the 18th century,
وحتى أواخر القرن الثامن عشر
and it was pretty apparent why.
وقد كان السبب واضحاً
Tapestries were portable. You could roll them up,
وذلك بسبب سهولة نقلهم، حيث يمكن لفّهم
send them ahead of you, and in the time
ودحرجتهم، وأثناء القيام بتعليقهم
it took to hang them up, you could transform a cold,
يمكن تحويل غرفة كئيبة
dank interior into a richly colored setting.
إلى مكان مليئ بالألوان
Tapestries effectively provided a vast canvas
المنسوجات كانت وسيلة مهمة
on which the patrons of the day could depict the heroes
لزعماء تلك الفترة لتخليد ذكرى الأبطال
with whom they wanted to be associated,
مع من تمنوا أن يتم تخليد ذكراهم معهم
or even themselves,
أو حتى مع أنفسهم
and in addition to that, tapestries were hugely expensive.
ولقد كانت تلك المنسوجات باهظة الثمن أيضاً.
They required scores of highly skilled weavers
لقد كان نسجهم يتم من قبل أفضل النساجين
working over extended periods of time
الذين يعملون لساعات طويلة
with very expensive materials -- the wools, the silks,
مستخدمين أدوات باهظة الثمن -- كالصوف والحرير
even gold and silver thread.
حتى خيوط الذهب والفضة
So, all in all, in an age when the visual image
إجمالاً، في العصور التي كان فيها التصوير المرئي
of any kind was rare, tapestries were an incredibly potent
نادراً، كانت المنسوجات تشكل وسيلة هامة
form of propaganda.
للدعاية
Well, I became a tapestry historian.
حسناً، أصبحت مؤرخا للمنسوجات
In due course, I ended up as a curator
وتدريجياً مع الوقت، انتهى بي المطاف
at the Metropolitan Museum, because I saw the Met
كأمين المتحف المطراني، لأنني أرى أن المطرانية
as one of the few places where I could organize
هي إحدى الأماكن القليلة التي يمكنني فيها تنظيم
really big exhibitions about the subject
معارض كبيرة لأمور
I cared so passionately about.
أهتم بها بشغف
And in about 1997, the then-director Philippe de Montebello
وفي عام 1997 قام المدير حينها "فيليب دي مونتيبيلو"
gave me the go-ahead to organize an exhibition
بمنحي الموافقة على تنظيم معرض
for 2002. We normally have these very long lead-in times.
خاص بـ2002. عادة نقوم بها عن أزمنة بعيدة
It wasn't straightforward. It's no longer a question
ليس الأمر سهلاً. لم يعد الموضوع مجرد
of chucking a tapestry in the back of a car.
تحميل المنسوجة في السيارة
They have to be wound on huge rollers,
بل يجب لفها على بكرات كبيرة
shipped in oversized freighters.
ومن ثم شحنها على شاحنات ضخمة
Some of them are so big we had, to get them into the museum,
بعضها كبير جداً لدرجة أنه علينا
we had to take them up the great steps at the front.
إدخالها عبر البوابات الكبير في مقدمة المتحف
We thought very hard about how to present this
فكرنا ملياً في كيفية تعريف هذه
unknown subject to a modern audience:
القطع الغير مألوفة للجمهور المعاصر:
the dark colors to set off the colors that remained
الألوان الغامقة التي تتوازن مع الألوان المتبقية
in objects that were often faded;
في الأجسام التي تختفي عادة
the placing of lights to bring out the silk and the gold thread;
الإضاءة المناسبة التي تؤدي لإظهار خيوط الذهب
the labeling.
الترتيب
You know, we live in an age where we are so used
نحن نعيش في عصر اعتدنا فيه
to television images and photographs,
على الصور التي نراها في التلفاز
a one-hit image. These were big, complex things,
الصور ذات البعد الواحد. أما هذه فهي قطع كبيرة ومعقدة
almost like cartoons with multiple narratives.
تقريباً كرسومات كرتونية ذات أبعاد متعددة
We had to draw our audience in, get them to slow down,
اضطررنا لاجتذاب الجمهور أولاً ولفت نظرهم
to explore the objects.
لاستكشاف هذه القطع
There was a lot of skepticism. On the opening night,
راودتنا الكثير من الشكوك في ليلة الافتتاح
I overheard one of the senior members of staff saying,
سمعت أحد المشرفين يقول
"This is going to be a bomb."
"ستكون قنبلة"
But in reality, in the course of the coming weeks and months,
لكن حقيقةً، في الأسابيع والأشهر التي تلتها
hundreds of thousands of people came to see the show.
مئات الألاف من الزوار، جاؤوا ليحضروا العرض
The exhibition was designed to be an experience,
لقد تم الأعداد للمعرض لكي يكون تجربة،
and tapestries are hard to reproduce in photographs.
ومن الصعب أن يعاد تصوير هذه المنسوجات
So I want you to use your imaginations,
أريدكم أن تستخدموا مخيلاتكم
thinking of these wall-high objects,
في التفكير بهذه القطع الكبيرة
some of them 10 meters wide,
بعضها يصل عرضها إلى عشرة أمتار
depicting lavish court scenes with courtiers and dandies
تحتوي على تصوير لمشاهد في المحاكم، فيها الخدم وكبار الشخصيات
who would look quite at home in the pages of the fashion press today,
التي تشبه الشخصيات التي نراها في مجلات الأزياء في يومنا هذا
thick woods with hunters crashing through the undergrowth
صيادين يعتلون عرباتهم المصنوعة من الخشب
in pursuit of wild boars and deer,
يطاردون الخنازير البرية والغزلان
violent battles with scenes of fear and heroism.
معارك عنيفة ذات مشاهد من الرعب والخوف
I remember taking my son's school class. He was eight at the time,
أتذكر أني حضرت مرة أحد دروس أبني ذو الثماني سنوات
and all the little boys, they kind of -- you know, they were little boys,
وجميع الأولاد حينها
and then the thing that caught their attention
لفت انتباههم
was in one of the hunting scenes there was a dog
كلب في أحد مقاطع الصيد
pooping in the foreground — (Laughter) —
كان يبترز في مقدمة اللقطة -(ضحك)-
kind of an in-your-face joke by the artist.
كان ذلك مزحة من الفنان
And you can just imagine them.
تخيلوا الأولاد حينها
But it brought it alive to them. I think they suddenly saw
لكن المزحة بعثت فيهم الاهتمام. أعتقد أنهم حينها
that these weren't just old faded tapestries.
رأوها بقيمتها الحقيقية، وأنها ليست مجرد منسوجة قديمة
These were images of the world in the past,
بل أنها صور للعالم في الماضي
and that it was the same for our audience.
وقد كان نفس التأثير في جمهورنا
And for me as a curator, I felt proud. I felt I'd shifted the needle a little.
وكأمين لذلك المتحف، شعرت بالفخر. شعرت أني قمت ببعض التغيير
Through this experience that could only be created
من خلال تلك التجربة التي من الممكن إجراءها في المتحف فقط
in a museum, I'd opened up the eyes of my audience --
قمت بلفت انتباه الجمهور
historians, artists, press, the general public --
من مؤرخين، فنانين، صحفيين، والناس العاديين
to the beauty of this lost medium.
لجمال هذه اللوحات
A few years later, I was invited to be the director
وبعدها بسنوات، تمت دعوتي لأكون مديراً
of the museum, and after I got over that --
للمتحف، فصدمت، وبعد انتهاء الصدمة
"Who, me? The tapestry geek? I don't wear a tie!" --
سألت نفسي، "أنا.؟ مهووس المنسوجات.؟ أنا لا أصلح لأكون مديراً!"
I realized the fact: I believe passionately in that
ومن ثم أدركت أنني أؤمن بشغف
curated museum experience.
بالتجربة التي قمنا بها في المتحف
We live in an age of ubiquitous information,
نحن نعيش في عصر المعلومات المتوافرة في كل مكان،
and sort of "just add water" expertise,
وخبراء التجارب البسيطة،
but there's nothing that compares with the presentation
لكن لايوجد ما يمكن مقارنته مع تقديم
of significant objects in a well-told narrative,
قطعة رائعة بشكل قصة كاملة و جيدة
what the curator does, the interpretation of a complex,
مايقوم به الوصي على المتحف، هو شرح هذه
esoteric subject, in a way that retains the integrity
اللوحة المعقدة والدالة على حدث معين، بطريقة تحفظ تكامل
of the subject, that makes it -- unpacks it
اللوحة، بطريقة تفرغ مضمونها
for a general audience.
وتقدمه للجمهور.
And that, to me, today, is now the challenge and the fun
وهذا هو التحدي الذي استمتع به اليوم
of my job, supporting the vision of my curators,
في عملي، وهو دعم رؤية الأوصياء لدي
whether it's an exhibition of Samurai swords,
سواء كان في معرض لسيوف الساموراي
early Byzantine artifacts, Renaissance portraits,
أو تحف بيزانطية قديمة، أو صور من عصر النهضة
or the show we heard mentioned earlier,
أو عن المنسوجات التي تحدثنا عنها سابقاً
the McQueen show, with which we enjoyed
عرض "مكوين"، الذي استمتعنا به
so much success last summer.
وحققنا نجاحاً باهراً به الصيف الماضي
That was an interesting case.
كانت قصة مهمة
In the late spring, early summer of 2010, shortly after
في أواخر الخريف، بدايات صيف 2010 بعد
McQueen's suicide,
انتحار "مكوين"
our curator of costume, Andrew Bolton, came to see me,
جاء وصي قسم الأزياء لدينا، أندرو بولتون، لرؤيتي
and said, "I've been thinking of doing a show on McQueen,
وقال: " أفكر بالقيام بعرض عن مكوين،
and now is the moment. We have to, we have to do it fast."
وأعتقد أن الوقت مناسب الآن، علينا القيام بالعرض الآن وبأسرع وقت"
It wasn't easy. McQueen had worked throughout his career
ليس أمراً سهلاً. مكوين عمل خلال مسيرته
with a small team of designers and managers
مع فريق من المصممين والمدراء
who were very protective of his legacy,
الحريصين على حماية إرثه
but Andrew went to London and worked with them
لكن أندرو كسب ثقتهم من خلال
over the summer and won their confidence, and that of
عمله معهم أثناء الصيف في لندن
the designers who created his amazing fashion shows,
كسب ثقة من صنع عروضه المبهرة من المصممين
which were works of performance art in their own right,
عروضه التي كانت أشبه بفن الأداء بأسلوبهم الخاص
and we proceeded to do something at the museum,
فاتفقنا أن نفتتح معرضاً
I think, we've never done before.
لم نقم بمثله من قبل
It wasn't just your standard installation.
لم يقتصر المعرض على وضع المعروضات وحسب
In fact, we ripped down the galleries to recreate
لقد أعدنا توزيع المعروضات، لخلق
entirely different settings, a recreation of his first studio,
منظور جديد للمعروضات، بشكل يتحدث عن منشأها
a hall of mirrors,
كقاعة مرايا
a curiosity box,
صندوق فضول
a sunken ship, a burned-out interior,
سفينة غارقة، غرفة محترقة
with videos and soundtracks that ranged from
بالإضافة لمؤثرات صوتية ومرئية تتباين
operatic arias to pigs fornicating.
من أصوات الأجراس ، إلى تكاثر الخنازير
And in this extraordinary setting, the costumes
وفي هذا الترتيب الغير اعتيادي، بدت الأزياء
were like actors and actresses, or living sculptures.
وكأنها ممثلين وممثلات، أو شخصيات حيّة
It could have been a train wreck.
قد تبدو وكأنها حادث قطار
It could have looked like shop windows on Fifth Avenue
قد تبدو وكأنها شبابيك لمتجر في الجادة الخامسة
at Christmas, but because of the way that Andrew
خلال العيد، لكن بسبب تواصل أندرو
connected with the McQueen team, he was channeling
مع فريق مكوين، كان بإمكانه تجسيد
the rawness and the brilliance of McQueen,
قوة وعظمة مكوين
and the show was quite transcendant,
وقد قدمنا عرضاً مميزاً
and it became a phenomenon in its own right.
كان حدثاً مهماً ذو أسلوب خاص
By the end of the show, we had people queuing
في آخر العرض، تجمع الناس
for four or five hours to get into the show,
وانتظروا لمدة أربعة وخمسة ساعات، ليدخلوا إلى المعرض
but no one really complained.
ومع ذلك لم يشتكوا من مدة الانتظار
I heard over and over again, "Wow, that was worth it.
لقد سمعنا عبارات من الزوار كـ: "يا إلهي لقد استحق ذلك الانتظار"
It was a such a visceral, emotive experience."
أو: "لقد كان العرض عميقاً وعاطفياً."
Now, I've described two very immersive exhibitions,
لقد تحدثت لكم عن معرضين من المعارض المؤثرة جداً
but I also believe that collections, individual objects,
لكنني أعتقد أن المقتنيات و الأفراد
can also have that same power.
يمكنهم القيام بنفس التأثير
The Met was set up not as a museum of American art,
تلك المطرانية لم تبنى لتكون معرضاً للفن الأمريكي
but of an encyclopedic museum,
وإنما لتكون موسوعة
and today, 140 years later, that vision
واليوم، بعد 140 سنة، هذه الرؤية
is as prescient as ever,
قد تلاشت
because, of course, we live in a world of crisis,
لأننا نعيش في عالم الأزمات
of challenge, and we're exposed to it
والتحديات، ونحن على اطلاع عليها
through the 24/7 newsreels.
من خلال نشرات الأخبار
It's in our galleries that we can unpack the civilizations,
يمكننا من خلال معارضنا، تصوير المجتمعات المدنية
the cultures, that we're seeing the current manifestation of.
والحضارات، من خلال رؤيتنا للمظاهر الحالية
Whether it's Libya, Egypt, Syria,
سواء في ليبيا، مصر، أو سوريا
it's in our galleries that we can explain
من خلال معارضنا يمكننا التفسير
and give greater understanding.
وتوسيع الفهم
I mean, our new Islamic galleries are a case in point,
ما أعنيه، أن معارضنا الإسلامية الجديدةـ هي في صلب القضية
opened 10 years, almost to the week, after 9/11.
مضى عليها 10 سنوات، حيث بدأت بعد أسبوع من أحداث 11 سبتمبر
I think for most Americans, knowledge of the Islamic world
بالنسبة لمعظم الأمريكيين، كان العالم الإسلامي ليس من اهتماماتهم
was pretty slight before 9/11, and then it was thrust upon us
قبل أحداث 11 سبتمبر، ومن ثم صدمنا
in one of America's darkest hours,
بإحدى أكثر الأوقات سوداوية في تاريخ أمريكا
and the perception was through the polarization
والفكرة كانت عبر استيعاب
of that terrible event.
الحدث المروع
Now, in our galleries, we show 14 centuries
الآن، في معارضنا، نقوم بعرض القرن الرابع عشر
of the development of different Islamic cultures
في مراحل تطور الثقافات الاسلامية المختلفة
across a vast geographic spread,
عبر مساحة جغرافية واسعة
and, again, hundreds of thousands of people have come
ومئات الآلاف من الناس
to see these galleries since they opened last October.
قد زاروا هذه المعارض، منذ افتتاحها في اكتوبر الماضي
I'm often asked, "Is digital media replacing the museum?"
يسألني الناس عادة:" هل يتم استبدال المتاحف بالوسائل التكنلوجية الحديثة.؟"
and I think those numbers are a resounding rejection
أعتقد أن هذه الأعداد الهائلة من الزوار تمثل رفضاً صارخاً
of that notion. I mean, don't get me wrong,
لهذه الفكرة. لكن أتمنى أن لا يتم فهمي بشكل خاطئ
I'm a huge advocate of the Web.
أنا من المؤيدين الكبار للانترنت.
It gives us a way of reaching out to audiences
إنها تمنحنا الامكانية بالتواصل مع جمهورنا
around the globe, but nothing replaces the authenticity
حول العالم، لكن ليس هناك ما يمكن أن يكون بديلاً للأصالة
of the object presented with passionate scholarship.
التي تتمتع بها المعروضات، بالإضافة للإرث العاطفي الذي تقدمه
Bringing people face to face with our objects
إن وضع المعروضات وجهاً لوجه مع الناس
is a way of bringing them face to face with people
هو بطريقة ما تقريبهم من الناس
across time, across space, whose lives may have been
واختصار الزمان والمكان، وتعريفهم بحياة أناس
very different to our own, but who, like us,
تختلف كثيراً عن حياتنا، ومع ذلك فقد كان
had hopes and dreams, frustrations and achievements
لديهم أحلام وآمال مثلنا تماماً، إحباطات وأنجازات
in their lives. And I think this is a process
في حياتهم. وأعتقد أنه بهذه الطريقة
that helps us better understand ourselves,
نستطيع فهم أنفسنا بشكل أفضل
helps us make better decisions about where we're going.
واتخاذ قرارات أفضل في ماذا نريد أن نصبح
The Great Hall at the Met is one of the great portals of the world,
القاعة الرئيسية في المطرانية هي من أعظم المداخل نحو عالم
awe-inspiring, like a medieval cathedral.
مليئ بالدهشة والاستيحاء، ككتدارئية من العصور الوسطى
From there, you can walk in any direction
ومنها يمكنكم التوجه حيثما أردتم
to almost any culture.
باتجاه الحضارة التي تختارونها
I frequently go out into the hall and the galleries
أتردد إلى تلك القاعة وأتوجه نحو المعروضات
and I watch our visitors coming in.
وأتفرج على الزوار وهم يأتون
Some of them are comfortable. They feel at home.
بعضهم يشعر بالراحة، يشعرون وكأنهم في المنزل
They know what they're looking for.
يعرفون عن ماذا يبحثون.
Others are very uneasy. It's an intimidating place.
وبعضهم يشعرون بالتوتر. إنه مكان مثير للخوف
They feel that the institution is elitist.
يشعرون أن المنشأة، هي مكان للنخبة
I'm working to try and break down that sense of that elitism.
وأنا أعمل جاهداً لإزالة هذا الشعور
I want to put people in a contemplative frame of mind,
أريد أن يصل الناس إلى حالة تأملية
where they're prepared to be a little bit lost, to explore,
بحيث يكونوا مستعدين لنوع من الضياع، للبحث
to see the unfamiliar in the familiar,
لرؤية غير المألوف فيما هو مألوف
or to try the unknown.
أو لتجربة ما هو غامض
Because for us, it's all about bringing them face to face
لأنه بالنسبة لنا، الموضوع يتمحور بوضعهم وجهاً لوجه
with great works of art,
مع الأعمال الفنية الرائعة
capturing them at that moment of discomfort,
التقافهم في تلك اللحظة من اللاراحة
when the inclination is kind of to reach for your iPhone,
عندما يشعرون بالرغبة في استخدام أجهزتهم الذكية
your Blackberry, but to create a zone
وبدلاً من ذلك وضعهم في حالة
where their curiosity can expand.
يمكنهم فيها توسيع فضولهم
And whether it's in the expression of a Greek sculpture
وسواء كان ذلك عبر منحوت يوناني
that reminds you of a friend,
يذكرك بصديق
or a dog pooping in the corner of a tapestry,
أو عبر كلب يتبرز في زاوية إحدى الرسومات
or, to bring it back to my tutor Pietro,
أو، كما قال معلمي بيترو،
those dancing figures
هذه الشخصيات الراقصة
who are indeed knocking back the wine,
التي تحتسي الخمر
and that nude figure in the left foreground.
والشخصيات العارية في الناحية اليسرى
Wow. She is a gorgeous embodiment of youthful sexuality.
واو، إنها تجسيد رائع للجنس المليئ بالشباب
In that moment, our scholarship can tell you
في تلك اللحظة، مبادرتنا ستخبركم
that this is a bacchanal,
أن ذلك يمثل طقس عربدة
but if we're doing our job right,
لكن إذا قمنا بعملنا بشكل صحيح
and you've checked the jargon at the front door,
وقد رأيتم العبارة على الباب الأمامي
trust your instinct.
كن على ثقة بغرائزك.
You know it's an orgy.
ستعلمون أنها عربدة جماعية
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)